<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a letter sent to Monsieur de Beauuoir lord embassador for the French king vvherin is shewed the late attempt of a Iesuite who would haue killed the kings Maiestie with a knife.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13130A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847895</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12959</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02992)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12959)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 465:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a letter sent to Monsieur de Beauuoir lord embassador for the French king vvherin is shewed the late attempt of a Iesuite who would haue killed the kings Maiestie with a knife.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Short and are to be sold at the great north dore of Poules by Iohn Flasket,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In English and French.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ (-A4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12959:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12959:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Copie of a Letter ſent to Monsieur de Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoir Lord Embaſſador for the French king. <add>Henry IV</add>
            </p>
            <p>vvherin is ſhewed the late attempt of a Ieſuite who would haue killed the kings Maieſtie with a knife.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of the brazen serpent, probably passed to Peter Short in 1589-90 (McKerrow 118)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed by Peter Short and are to be ſold at the great north dore of Poules by Iohn Flasket. 1594</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12959:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12959:2"/>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>The Copie of a letter ſent to <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Beauvoir Lord Embaſſador for</hi> the French King.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>theſe are to giue you know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, of a ſudden and vnhappie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, which had like to haue falne vpon the king, had it not pleaſed God of his great mercie, miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly to preſerue his Maieſty from it. Your honour ſhall then vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that his Maieſty within litle more then an houre after his returne into the cittie of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> from out of <hi>Picardie,</hi> being as yet booted, and hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him the Lords and Princes of Conty, the Earles of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> and Saint Paule, and aboue thirty or forty of the chiefe Noblemen, and gentlemen of his court, as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty was buſie in receauing the <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Ragny,</hi> and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigny,</hi> whith had not before that time done their dutie, and allegeance to him, it happened a yoong fellowe, of verie ſmal ſtature, and not aboue eightéene, or ninetéene yeares of age, called <hi>Peter Chaſtel,</hi> the ſonne of a Merchant draper in this cittie, followed in amongſt the preaſe, into the cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, where the king himſelfe was, and thruſting forwarde as néere to the perſon of the kinge as hee coulde, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being noted or ſuſpected of any there preſent) he ſtrake at the king with a knife, whith he had brought to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, thinking to haue thruſt him into the belly. But ſo it fell out through the mightie prouidence of God, that the king in that verie inſtant, bowing himſelfe forwarde, to take vp the ſaide lordes of <hi>Ragny,</hi> and <hi>Montagny,</hi> (which kneled before him) the ſtroke lighted vpon his face on the vpper lip toward the right ſide, and brake one of his téeth, without dooing any further harme. The wretched caytife was preſently layed hold on, and denying the fact a while
<pb facs="tcp:12959:3"/> at the firſt, afterwards he voluntarily confeſſed it. Wee can as yet get nothing out of him, but that hee hath bene brought vp for the ſpace of this thrée years in the Colledge of the Ieſuites, in which place we ſuppoſe hee receaued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, to practiſe this treaſon. The firſt thing his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty thought vpon was to giue god thanks for his ſpecial grace, &amp; fauour at this time, in perſeruing him from this traiterous attempt, and cauſed a publike thankſgiuing to be ſong generally throughout the whole cittie, and the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens beſides made bonfiers in euerie ſtréete, for ioy of the kings deliuerance out of ſo great a danger. Thankes be to God, the hurte is ſo ſmall, that the kinge ſhall not néede to kéepe his bed for it: and we hope he ſhall be able to hold on with his determination, for the which hee haſtened his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to <hi>Paris,</hi> which is to ſolemnize the feaſte and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the order of the Holyghoſt. I thoght it beſt to aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe your honor hereof without any further delaie, for feare leaſt being preuented by others, not knowing the truth and certaintie of the matter, you and other the kings friendes and welwillers, ſhould thereby haue cauſe to be inwardly gréeued. His maieſties chiefe deſire is, that you cauſe a publicke thankeſgiuing to be offred vp to God for it, with earneſt praiers that it would pleaſe his diuine maieſtie, al waies to kéepe him vnder his mercifull protection, againſt ſuch bloudie and butcherlie practiſes, to which his enimies hauing ſo often recourſe, make manifeſt proofe to the world of their malicious intents, and finding that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them ouer to themſelues, they giue themſelues ouer to theſe moſt damnable and accurſed conſpiracies, which God I hope will bringe to confuſion, both them and thoſe that are the authors and deuiſers of them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>the 27. of December, 1594.</date> after their accompt.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="fre" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:12959:3"/>
               <head>The Copy of the ſame Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in French.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ous aurez icy la nouelle d'un malheureux accident qui a penſé arriuer au Roy, et comme il a pleu a Dieu par ſa miſericorde miraculeuſement l'en preſeruer Il ny auoit pas plus d'une heure que ſa Maieſté eſtoit arriuée en ceſte ville de retour de ſon voyage de Picardie, et e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoit encore toute bottée, Qu ayant autour d'elle Mesſieurs les Princes de Conty, Comte de Soiſſons et Comte de S. Paul, et plus de 30. ou 40. des prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipaux Seigneurs et Gentilzhommes de ceſte court, comme elle receuoit les ſeigneurs de Ragny &amp; de Montigny qui ne l'auoyent point encore ſaluéz vn Ieune garſon nommé Pierre Chaſtel fort petit et qui ne peut auoir que dixhuict ou dix neuf ans, fils d un marchant Drapier de ceſte ville lequel s'eſtoit gliſſé auec la trouppe dans la chambre s'aduance ſans eſtre quaſi aperceu de perſonne, et penſant luy donner d'un couſteau qu'il auoit dans le corps, le coup (par ce que ſa Maieſté s'eſtoit baiſſée pour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuer les ſuſdits ſieurs de Montigny et de Ragny qui la ſaluoyent) ne porta que dans la face ſur la leure haute du coſté droict, &amp; l'a entamée, et couppée vne dent. A l'inſtant ce miſerable a eſté prins, &amp; apres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoir vouleu vn peu defaduouer le fait incontinent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres il l‘a confeſſé ſans aucune force il ne s‘eſt enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re rien peu tirer de luy ſinon qu‘il á eſté nourry trois ans aux Colleges des Ieſuites, ou l‘on preſume qu‘il a receu ceſte inſtruction Ce dont ſa Maieſté s‘eſt vou leu: premierement ſouuenir a eſté de rendre graces a dieu de ceſte particulieire grace, qu‘illuy a faite de
<pb facs="tcp:12959:4"/> le garentir de ceſt aſſaſsinat, &amp; en à eſté à l‘inſtant chanté vn Te Deum en toutes les egliſes de ceſte vil le; à quoy les habitans ont adiouſté des feux de ioye par toutes les rues. Il y à (dieu mercy) ſi peu de mal, que pour cela ſa Maieſté, ne s'en mettra pas au lict de meilleuré heure, et eſperons, qu'elle ne perdra point la bonne occaſion, pour laquelle elle à auancé ſon retour, qui eſt, pour faire la feſte, &amp; ceremonie de l'ordre du ſainct Eſprit. Ie n'ay voluu tarder d'auan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage a vous donner ceſt aduis, affin que vous, &amp; les autres ſeruiteurs de ſa Maieſté eſtans preuenus de quelque autre, n'en ſoiez en peine. Mais ſa Maieſté deſire principalement que vous en faciez rendre gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces publiques a dieu, &amp; bonnes prieres, qu'il luy plaiſe la conſeruer touſiours en ſa ſaincte protection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre tels aſſaſsinats, auſquels puis que les ennemis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courent ſi ſouuent c'eſt bien vne preuue manifeſte de leur malheureuſe intention, &amp; comme ſe ſentans abandonnez de Dieu, ils s'abandonnent aux reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons les plus execrables, que i'eſpere, qu'il confondra touſiours a leur ruine, &amp; confuſion.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>A Paris <date>27. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb. 1594.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:12959:4"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
